Guide to the Ireland House Oral History Collection AIA.030
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Ireland House Oral History Collection
2005-2017
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Glucksman Ireland House
AIA.030
4 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons
105 Gigabytes in 146 recordings
The Ireland House Oral History Collection contains interviews of Irish and Irish Americans conducted between 2005 and 2017 by undergraduates, doctoral students, and faculty in the Irish Studies program at New York University, as well as staff of the Glucksman Ireland House. Topics covered in the interviews include childhood, education, family life, immigration experience, working life, political activity, and cultural activity. Many of the narrators were active in immigration reform, Irish republican politics, and the Irish American community in New York City.
Custodial History Note
Interviews were conducted by students in the Irish Studies program. Materials are transferred to the Archives after access copies of interviews have been created on DVDs and transcripts typed up.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Irish Immigration Reform Movement Records AIA 016
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with restrictions as noted per individual interview.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by interviewee. Dates recorded refer to date of interview.
Historical Note
Multi-generational interviews conducted since 2005 as part of an undergraduate oral history course for the Irish Studies program at New York University, under the auspices of Glucksman Ireland House. Subsequent interviews have been conducted by Ireland House staff.
Scope and Contents
The Ireland House Oral History Collection contains interviews of Irish and Irish Americans conducted between 2005 and 2017 by undergraduates, doctoral students, and faculty in the Irish Studies program at New York University, as well as staff of the Glucksman Ireland House. The oral histories document the lives of people born between the 1910s and 1980s, working in Ireland and the United States (U.S.) as diplomats, business owners, laborers, educators, journalists, lawyers, members of Catholic orders, politicians, musicians, and actors. The interviews were conducted in Ireland and in the U.S., mainly in English, with at least one interview conducted in Irish. Topics covered include childhood, education, family life, immigration experience, working life, political activity, and cultural activity. Many of the narrators were active in immigration reform, Irish republican politics, and the Irish American community in New York City and other American cities with large Irish American populations.
Accruals Note
Additional accruals to this collection are expected.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
An additional accretion was donated in 2018 by Marion Casey. The accession number associated with this gift is 2018.100.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Transcripts.; Irish Americans -- Social life and customs.; Oral histories (literary works); Northern Ireland -- History -- 1968-1998; Irish Americans -- Interviews; Irish -- Interviews.; Ireland -- Emigration and immigration.; Emigration and immigration law.; Minihane, Sean; Burns, Edward, 1968-; Sexton, John Edward, 1942-; King, Peter T., 1944-; Benson, Sean; Irish Northern Aid Committee
- A
  - Alcock, Leslie, 2015; cuid34753 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_51)
    Biographical Note
    Leslie Alcock was born in 1984 in Dublin, Ireland. She attended St. Leo's Mercy Convent in Carlow, County Carlow, Ireland and graduated from Maynooth University in Maynooth, County Kildare, Ireland in 2005. Alcock immigrated to the United States in 2012 to work at the Irish Immigration Center in Upper Darby, Pennsylvania.
    Scope and Contents
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll at the Irish Immigration Center in Upper Darby, Pennsylvania on April 16, 2015. The interview contains Leslie Alcock's family and career history. Alcock recounts her memories of her leadership training in youth groups during her teens, which inspired her to gain her degree in social work. She describes the process of gaining a position as a social worker at the Irish Immigration Center of Philadelphia. Alcock elaborates on her work with the senior citizens of Philadelphia in her social work at the Irish Immigration Center. Alcock describes her responsibilities of planning and hosting public programming at the Irish Immigration Center for senior citizens.
  - Allen, Sandie, May 2, 2013; cuid34473 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Historical/Biographical Note
    Sandie Allen (b. London, England, 1966) is an accomplished photographer who has documented events in Boston's Irish community for almost three decades.
  - Anderson, Anne, 2016; cuid34754 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_61)
    Anne Anderson was born in 1952 in Clonmel, County Tipperary, Ireland. She received her bachelor's degree from University College Dublin in 1972 and her legal degree from the Honourable Society of King's Inns in Dublin. In 1972 she joined Ireland's Department of Foreign Affairs. Throughout her career she served in various positions in the European Union, the United Nations, and the United States. Anderson was Ireland's first female ambassador to the United States in 2013 and was in that position at the time of the 2016 interview.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll at the Consulate-General of Ireland in Boston, Massachusetts on December 1, 2016. The interview focuses Anne Anderson's education and career in Ireland's Department of Foreign Affairs. Anderson discusses her parents, her extended family, and her early education. She discusses her decision to attend University College Dublin (UCD) rather than Trinity College Dublin and recounts her experience studying at UCD. She recounts her decision to join Ireland's Department of Foreign Affairs (DFA) in 1972 and her early experiences in the DFA. She describes the role of women in the DFA, from her early experiences as one of two women in her department to her groundbreaking role as Ireland's first female ambassador to the United States (US). She also discusses emigration from Ireland to Australia in the 2000s and the difference in perception between emigration to Australia and to the US.
- B
  - Barry, Dan, Nov 3, 2011; cuid34474 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Dan Barry (b. 1958) is a Pulitzer Prize-winning writer for The New York Times and has covered many topics, including the World Trade Center disaster and the damage to the Gulf Coast from Hurricane Katrina. He is the author of three books, including the autobiography Pull Me Up (2004).
  - Behan, Joe, May 4, 2011; cuid34475 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Joe Behan (b. Dublin, Co. Dublin, 1961) has been Head Coach of the New York University Men's Soccer team since 1996. He brought the team their first two NCAA Division III Championship appearances and was named Coach of the Year in 1999 and 2010.
  - Beirne, Hilary, Oct 29, 2009; cuid34476 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Content Note
    Hilary Beirne was interviewed on the 26th of October, 2009 at the Glucksman Ireland House at New York University by James Herron and Linda Dowling Almeida. The topics discussed were wide and varied, starting with his background, growing up in County Roscommon, Ireland and following through his life from college days to working in Ireland in the 1970s and '80s to immigrating to the United States in the late '80s and ending with his distinguished work with the St. Patrick's Day Parade.
    Beirne discusses his early life, growing up with nine brothers and sisters in a large farmhouse that his father, a veterinary surgeon, purchased around the time Beirne was born. He talks about his experiences in National School, and the effects that the small learning community, corporal punishment, and religious doctrine had on his education. He went to secondary school, earning high enough marks to attend college and earn a degree in agricultural studies. He discusses his first few jobs in Ireland, where he worked on projects that redesigned the way Irish farms operate and store various crops.
    He eventually left his job and immigrated to the U.S. to become a science teacher in the Bronx. It was at this time that he became involved in the New York City St. Patrick's Day Parade, upon which a large portion of this interview is based. Beirne discusses the finances, the history, the operations and the future of the parade in great detail. He provides an excellent behind-the-scenes view of the production of one of the largest parades in the world. Beirne also discusses, in great detail, the various other Irish fraternal clubs of which he is a member.
    As a teacher, Beirne discusses his instructing methods and how he engages the student. He also spends time discussing how he became a teacher and the reasons why. He also talks about what he thinks makes a good teacher, and the necessary traits to perform the job well.
    He then returns to a broader discussion on why Irish-American heritage is important to this country, stating, "40 million Americans trace their heritage back to Ireland…" in order to show just how important the parade is.
    Throughout the interview, Beirne takes breaks from discussing his life and the parade to talk about his family. He discusses his twin brother and the unique skills he possesses that his twin does not and vice versa. He discusses the odd relationship his siblings (2 brothers, 7 sisters) had with his parents, specifically, the love and strong bond they all had with their mother and poor relationship they had with their father. He also talks about the day he left Ireland and the effects his leaving had on his mother.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz CDR420. The interview is 2 hours and 28 minutes long, on 3 CDs. The interview took place on October 29, 2009, and the interviewers were James Herron and Linda Dowling Almedia.
    Related Archival Materials
    Interview with Tommy Smyth. Ireland House Oral History Collection, Archives of Irish America, New York University. Interview with Treasa Goodwin Smyth. Ireland House Oral History Collection, Archives of Irish America, New York University.
    Other Finding Aids Note
    This interview has been logged at ten-minute intervals, and the Word file is available upon request at tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu.
    Hilary Beirne (b. Boyle, Co. Roscommon, 1961) is a science teacher who emigrated to New York in 1988. He is a longtime member of the New York St. Patrick's Day Parade Committee and the nephew of the late Frank Beirne.
  - Beirne, Thomas, 2014; cuid34755 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_25)
    Thomas Beirne was born in 1968 in New York, New York. He graduated from Manhattan College with a bachelor's degree in civil engineering in 1990. In 2014, he was the district president of the New York chapter of the Ancient Order of the Hibernians and worked in construction management.
    This interview was conducted by Danielle Zach on September 9, 2014 at New York University's Glucksman Ireland House in New York, New York. This interview covers Thomas Beirne's early life in the Woodlawn neighborhood of the Bronx, New York and in Yonkers, New York. He recounts his memories of his father's involvement in political activism for Irish Americans and the Ancient Order of the Hibernians. Describing his position in 2014 as the district president of the Ancient Order of the Hibernians, he details his involvement with the St. Patrick's Day Parade planning committee.
  - Benson, Sean, Nov 29, 2005; cuid34477 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    Sean Benson (b. 1960), was one of the organizers of the Irish Immigration Reform Movement. He is the former Executive Director of the Emerald Isle Immigration Center and remains a member of its board.
  - Blancato, Robert, 2015; cuid34756 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_59)
    Robert Blancato was born in the Bronxville neighborhood of the Bronx, New York in 1951. He graduated in 1970 from Iona Preparatory High School in New Rochelle, New York and attended Georgetown University in Washington, D.C.
    This interview was conducted by Danielle Zach on August 3, 2015 in Washington, D.C. The interview covers Robert Blancato's early life and career working for Congressman Mario Biaggi. He describes his internship with Congressman Biaggi in 1972 and how it resulted in a job as a congressional aide after graduating from college. He recounts his involvement with the founding of the Ad Hoc Congressional Committee for Irish Affairs in 1977. He describes the goal of the committee to understand the conflict in Northern Ireland and make a peace forum where all parties involved in the conflict could be represented. Blancato recalls his trip to Ireland in 1978 where he personally negotiated with Gerry Adams to create a peace forum. He describes how his interactions with the Ancient Order of Hibernians and the Irish Northern Aide helped him build the Congressional Committee for Irish Affairs.
  - Boucher, Jack, Jan 23, 2009; cuid34478 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Jack Boucher (b. New York, New York, 1938), a union bartender and Vietnam veteran, is the son of immigrants from County Leitrim, and County Sligo, Ireland. Raised in New York's Washington Heights, he was a member of the youth gang the Jesters.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PCM660. The interview took place on January 23, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Bowden, Noreen, 2016; cuid34757 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_90)
    Noreen Bowden was born in 1969 in Suffern, New York. She received her bachelor's degree from Notre Dame University in Notre Dame, Indiana and her master's degree in public policy from the John F. Kennedy School of Government at Harvard University in Cambridge.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll at New York University's Elmer Holmes Bobst Library in New York, New York on April 28, 2016. The interview covers Noreen Bowden's family and her working life. Bowden discusses her family, their immigration and work experiences, and the death of her mother in 1986. She discusses her involvement with the Irish Immigration Reform Movement and the Irish Immigration Center in Boston in the 1990s. She discusses her work for multiple online Irish news sources, including VitualIrish.com, the Irish Emigrant>'s online newspaper, and her own website, www.Globalirish.ie, which covers issues relating to Irish identity and the Irish diaspora.
  - Bowles, Dympna Farrell, Apr 19, 2011; cuid34479 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Dymphna Farrell Bowles (b. Ennistown, Co. Meath, Ireland, 1922) a long-time resident of New Rochelle, New York, moved to Belfast in 1942. She married there in 1947 and later emigrated to the United States with five young children. Her sixth child was born in New York.
  - Boyer, Sandy, 2014; cuid34758 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_11)
    Sandy Boyer was born in 1943 in New York, New York and was raised in Croton-on-Hudson, New York. He was a political activist and journalist. He died in 2016.
    This interview was conducted by Danielle Zach at New York University's Glucksman Ireland House on June 30 and July 7, 2014. The interview covers Sandy Boyer's childhood and his political activity as an adult. Boyer discusses his childhood and his parents, including their backgrounds, careers, and their membership in the Communist Party of the United States of America. He discusses his involvement in Irish republican causes from the 1970s to the 1990s, particularly Irish Northern Aid Committee (NORAID), the popularity of fundraising through pub socials, and the role of Irish music in politics. He discusses the relationship between Irish and Irish American political organizations including NORAID, National H-Block / Armagh Committee, the Irish Republican Socialist Party, People's Democracy, and Sinn Fein. He discusses multiple Irish political prisoners to whom he lent his support including Marian Price, Martin Corey, Gerry Conlon, and Gerry McGeough.
  - Boylan, Jim, Feb 26, 2009; cuid34480 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    In the interview, Boylan focuses on growing up in 1940s/50s Harlem; the racial dynamics of Harlem and the Irish living in that setting; the impact of Puerto Ricans in his neighbourhood; how Irishness is passed on to next generation; 1950s migrants coming to stay with them; and his parents first trip back to Ireland.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 160 minutes long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place on February 26, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
    Jim Boylan (b. New York, New York, 1941), is the son of 1920s immigrants from County Monaghan,Ireland. He grew up in Harlem, New York, and spent his career working in telecommunications.
  - Brady, Elizabeth, 2014; cuid34759 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_18)
    Elizabeth Brady was born in 1930 in Ballyshannon, County Donegal, Ireland. She immigrated to the United States in 1956, settling in Chicago, Illinois. She met her husband, Joseph Brady, in 1958 and was married in 1960. They returned to Ireland in 1967 and settled on a farm in Tullaghan in County Leitrim. They had two children.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll in Mullingar, County Westmeath, Ireland on July 28, 2014. The interview covers Elizabeth Brady's early life in Ireland, her working life in Ireland and the United States (US), and her family. Brady describes her parents, her father's experiences working in the US and Ireland, and their extended families. She discusses her education, her working life, and describes the different jobs she held in Ireland and the US. She describes her preparations for immigrating to the US, her voyage via ship in 1956, and her impressions of New York, New York and Chicago, Illinois. She describes her husband, their married life together, and their decision to move from Chicago to a farm in County Leitrim, Ireland. She recounts her family's life on their farm and their social lives.
  - Branley, Mary, Aug 1, 2013; cuid34481 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Mary Branley (b. Sligo Town, Co. Sligo, Ireland, 1962) studied Multicultural Education in Boston, taught in an inner city school, then returned to Ireland where she is a teacher and poet.
  - Brazil, Áine, 2016; cuid34760 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_60)
    Áine Brazil was born in 1956 in Galway, County Galway, Ireland. She received her bachelor's degree from University College Galway in 1977 and her master's degree from Imperial College in London, England in 1980. She established the Máire Brazil Prize at National University of Ireland Galway to provide a four-year scholarship for women pursuing engineering degrees. She married in 1982. At the time of the 2016 interview, Brazil was working as a structural engineer at Thornton Tomasetti in New York, New York.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll at Áine Brazil's office at Thornton Tomasetti in New York, New York on April 28, 2016. The interview covers Brazil's family, education, and working life in the United States. Brazil discusses her parents, including their families, education, and careers. She discusses her education, citing her teachers and the availability of honors math at her school as critical to her professional path. She recounts her experiences at University College Galway as one of three women in a class of 63 and discusses her decision to major in structural engineering. She discusses working London, England; entering a master's program in Imperial College in London; and her experiences as an Irish person in England in the 1980s. She describes her job responsibilities and her work on the Hudson Yards project in Manhattan in detail.
  - Brennan, Gerry, 2016; cuid34761 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_77)
    Gerry Brennan was born in 1952 in Dublin, Ireland and was raised in Naas, County Kildare. In 1973, he graduated from the Dublin Institute of Technology and immigrated to the United States (US). He has owned a number of properties in the US and Ireland, including many popular Irish bars in Boston, Massachusetts. He married and has three sons.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll at Gerry Brennan's home in Chestnut Hill, Massachusetts on August 16, 2016. The interview covers Brennan's early life in Ireland and his working life in the United States (US). Brennan discusses his family, including the education and working life of his parents. He recounts immigrating to the US in 1973, settling in Boston, and establishing a painting and renovation business with his brother. He explains that they were able to establish this business despite not having visas or Green Cards and discusses their expansion of their business in the 1980s. He explains the way in which he gained a Green Card and the expansion of his real estate investments after this change in his resident status. He describes the bars he owned in Boston, including the Brendan Behan Pub in Jamaica Plain and the Thirsty Scholar in Cambridge, and discusses the role of these bars in the Irish and Irish American culture in the Boston area. Brennan also discusses his real estate investments in County Kildare, Ireland and the work ethic his parents instilled in him and his siblings.
  - Brennan, John, Oct 19, 2012; cuid34482 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    John Brennan (b. Co. Kerry, Ireland, 1972) worked in Henry Ford & Son Ltd in Cork from 1948-1953 when he immigrated to NY, served in the US Army, and received his BA in Economics from Fordham University. He spent most of his life working in insurance.
  - Brosnan, Maureen, 2014; cuid34762 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_64)
    Maureen Brosnan was born in 1929 in the Bronx, New York. She received her bachelor's degree from Fordham University in the Bronx in 1949.
    This interview was conducted by Miriam Nyhan at Maureen Brosnan's home in the Bronx, New York on September 25, 2014. The interview covers Brosnan's life in the Bronx. Brosnan describes her parents, their early lives in Ireland, and stories of their immigration to the United States (US). She recounts her father's experience in the Irish Republican Brotherhood in Ireland and his activities with other Irish republican organizations in the US in the early to mid 20th century. She discusses working in advertising agencies in New York City while attending Fordham University in the Bronx in the late 1940s. She recounts her experiences visiting Ireland throughout her life and her participation in Irish American organizations in New York City throughout her life.
  - Browne, Anna, 2014; cuid34763 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_17)